so internally like 32 parts the body you
can't see you will brain your lungs test
onyx etc so that's when you think about
it when you want to contemplate your
brain your lungs then that idea is there
a thought is there mmm but is it so now
I'm attending that thought and then I'm
picking up the sign oh those things yeah
well there's a difference that's exactly
the only way people who people would
approach this the only way they would
know how is through attending in other
words they will be attending that
thought as if that's really attending to
your brain which you can't so the only
way to see these body parts correctly in
the relevant concentration memories
indirectly without attending them
directly as objects of your attention
you have to discern them as that because
of which you are here living attending
to things so that's the difference when
people do well that's the difference
between doing your Diwali contemplation
right name wrongly wrongly it's
basically just just repeating these
parts and visualizing them and thinking
that that somehow I mean you might
provide you an initial kind of reduction
of central craving because you never
think about those things but soon very
soon you can use it and will become
meaningless because you can't you can't
see those things directly that's why I
mean potential butter the stallion turn
on the 6n space is the ultimate indirect
it's the ultimate peripheral it's the
ultimate that because of which there is
the wall for you you are perceiver you
are the consumer of it that's why when
when the when the Buddha describes these
are the six the sixth sense base it's
described in the almost external medical
manner the fleshy eye the nose and so on
because that's that's the closest you
can see it you can't
you can see directly you cannot attend
to your eye you can only attend to the
object but that's not the eye because of
which you see things but you miss
conceiving it that that's the eye
because of which you see things you
start assuming that you can attend that
because of which your attention is there
you have to stop trying to attend the
eye the nose but start discerning it as
a basis as a physical basis for the
world to exist for you within you so in
the same sense like you can be attending
in the cup attending at the table
attending it an image of your brain but
your just regarding these things is
overly objective I like objects of your
attention so to speak in a way they have
something in common they are all
material but you don't want to regard
your brain just as you regard a cup
because cup is insignificant to you you
want to discern the dead objective brain
that you are thinking about is the
reason for your subjectivity because of
which you are able to attend to the idea
of the brain in the first place so so
what you just said there must keep
saying it to myself and against a little
muscle well you might have to initially
to remind yourself to kind of recreate
the the right order of things that you
can well on it but after a while you
don't have to after all you enough just
because you will know how to look
indirectly you will know how to see
things without having to look at them
and that's another thing I think people
might miss miss miss understanding these
the talks on YouTube and stop when we
mentioned you know the simultaneous
presence people might end up thinking
it's like a two things at the same time
momentarily present in front of me but
when I say simultaneous presence the way
the Superstock body it's basically two
things are present on two different
levels which means they're not very equal
which means they're not very equal
present at the same time for a second or
two and you must catch them both at the
same time no you're just trying to catch
one thing again you can divide it into
million of sub parts your attention is
still looking at that foreground of an
object so when we talk about
simultaneous presence that's why I keep
saying it induce the peripheral and
yours which means in this case say you
have a you have a an image of your brain
that you don't overly attend as a random
object in the world that you tell them
to yourself see this body is not mine no
you see that image of the brain you stop
misconceiving it as we would say and you
start discerning at it that's the
closest the closest you can get to that
which actually your life depends upon to
that form the closest you can get is
through these images of the brain lungs
heart blood and so on you realize all of
them stand for that because of which you
are conscious here living this life but
you can't possibly enter that brain as
in access it through your perception or
anything like that because it precedes
it but you can know that the image of
the brain that you have that on that
peripheral level is that because of
which you're able to again be here and
now present and attend to these various
other things that arise in other words
then when you stop thinking about the
bring your knowledge that that's the
order of your experience as in you are
undermined by the matter doesn't change
and that's what I mean it's
simultaneously present you don't have to
keep that you can you can forget about
it rightly it will basically will
constitute rightful forgetfulness which
is when your forgetfulness then does not
induce a vision anymore
but you don't have to keep that you it's
impossible to keep thinking about
everything all the time yeah that's well
let's think something you have to do yet
because you can't really get brain
exactly could you just keep them make forcing it
could you just keep them make forcing it
into the foreground and then you fail to
see what what what the peripheral there
is which means you you have now over the
misconceived that brain and you making
it into an object of your perception
which is impossible for it to be I
cannot see itself but because one wants
to say you think about the brain right
with peripheral you discerned image of
the brain in you recognize there is the
brain in here because of which my
experience still exists and then you
stop thinking about it and then three
hours later you think about it again
and it's important here to induce the
attitude if you have to eventually you
will recognize it as such it's important
when three hours later you think about
the brain again you recognize that it's
the same brain that has been here this
whole time the fact that you forgot
about it did not make it not there so
then even back same like with moods or
feelings say you have a present more the
reason it's it's it's sort of farriner
agreeable but then you know you you
start attending to more particular
things doing and then you don't go
around thinking how agreeable your days
but then later for six hours later you
sort of look back and you remember it
again it's agreeable it's the same mood
and that's what I mean you have to let
it and you're basically that means that
when you bring it back you don't make
videos but you recognize it as it has
been enduring on its own that's how you
start this learning the simultaneous
principle I'm talking about simultaneous
in a sense that yeah the general mood
the general notion of the matter being
there for example in the contemplation
of the body it's been their enduring on
its own whether you thought about it or
not so when you do remember you you will
eventually stopped giving priority to I
remember this and I am attending this
and now I'm practicing this you just
find it so it's very similar nicely
present with everything else you do when
you don't attend to that it's the
necessary basis basically for your
action for your choice for your
attention for when can you because always you want
for when can you because always you want
to develop them domain as you say want
it develop the domain make background
don't mean hmm so one once to then
develop it I don't care nothing to do
now okay
I'm gonna develop that but then I think
about it what I Lily not forget about it
yeah you develop it by learning how to
discern that it's already there sure but
then then you feel you have to forget
about it
after a minute after a minute that's
fine then when you remember about it you
want to abandon the attitude of I must
restart this practice because I've
forgot about it but instead you want to
develop recognition oh yeah
it's still there that's pretty much the
crucial difference then I'm talking
about work cuz many people say be here
now be present just feel just this it's
just like that and whatnot but it all
you've all just come back to the present
moment come back to the present moment
you wanna recognize it when you come
back to the present moment you can only
do so because it was there in during
beforehand it was there so then you
realize you can't forget about it
even if you want you are responsible for
your own ignorance because you are
responsible for the attitude of thinking
it's on you to hold it in front of you
and that's the only way of existing so
you forget about it after a minute then
you remember it after five minutes and
then you think oh I forgot about it I
must I must do it again now as if you
are the one who does it from the scratch
no till each time there is sugar Rises
you include that attitude in that
mindfulness as well it's not rooted in
you it's rooted in the enduring
background it's in that's for the
mandated by the way the ultimate
background a cheat a limiter and that's
why he knows the mind and exhausted or
as frankerz the
translated these states that people
obviously almost automatically
appropriate are the states of mind as
such introduced five days later you look
at you remember it again the only reason
can remember it is because it's still
very enduring to some extent and what
will that do this kind of practice of
mindfulness can you cannot just well you
can't be treading water with it if you
keep doing it it is forcing you
basically to shift the center of your
experience from your sense of self onto
the background of the things and even
the actual things that you are attending
because you realize that they're there
because of the background in other words
you start squeezing your own sense of
self out there is no room for it in the
experience because whether you look at
the background whether you're attending
the foreground you realize this it can
be done so only because these things
endure on their own beforehand and with
terms of the peripheral as I said six
days later you remember something it's
because for six days it's been enduring
there the state of mind so that's how
you stop worrying about I must not
forget I must not forget but instead
stop focusing on I must discern whenever
I remember I must not miss conceive
whenever I remember and the most
fundamental misconceiving is mine as in
I am here the center not this thing that
I remember because of which I am in the
first place
so whatever okay so whenever you your
mind whatever you attend to at any given
time that must introduce a remembering
of of the way things well you don't even
have to say that you can just say
whatever you attend to just be aware of
of what you're doing so include yourself
in that picture and then with that sense
of self is that's already where the
background is but now instead of instead
of sort of feeling that each time you
remember you must restart and then hold
as long as you
you drop that whole attitude or stop
paying attention to it but instead
whenever you remember even if it's once
a day on a day that you are very
distracted you still don't try to look or now
you still don't try to look or now
remember I must hold it no I remember it
is already there a reason beforehand not
mine not for me not myself cannot be
mine and that automatically affects
everything else within that background
we did that peripheral but it's gonna
take time to see that because now the
emphasis is on what I attend
that's what matters so that's what you
try to keep okay so I'm attending on to
this so I'm attending on to this then
you forget anything oh now I have to do
it again no you don't because the only
reason you can attend to anything is
because they're given as an option which
means it exists on the peripheral where
the possibilities exist so practically
speaking you think about your brain your
heart your lungs you can attempt it
directly if you want you say but don't
is concede it don't think that it's that
read that really which heart is it's an
approximation that you determine whether
it's gonna be right if you don't miss
consume it or wrong if you miss consume
it so practically you think about there
is this brain there in these bones there
is Phineas there is this flesh and that
is the reason for me being able to look
at these bones seniors so once you start
attending to it correctly there is the
heart the lungs and so on that's it you
think you don't keep to try to keep it
in front of it because it's not in front
of it you're looking at this event which
determines your experience as you know
then the necessary condition for which
is presence of the matter so once you
brought it to your mind you do so in
order to let it go you don't have to eat
you want to learn how not to have to
actively think about it in order for it
to be regarded as it's present it's real
so you think about this various parts of
the body as
as the reason for your experience and
then you let it let it be and then say
you still mindful Oh like we can do it
now think about your heart and then give
you the significance in the sense of
don't just think about what the picture
of a heart but think your beating heart
right now you can actually feel beating
do you have any volitional power over it
can you say can you tell it to slow down
can you tell it to speed up no can you
tell it to stop
can you tell you to never stop can you
tell you to not get sick
can you tell you to not get blocked and
hold up none of it means it's actually
inaccessible to you yet now at the same
time think about what is the hard word
to stop now would you be able to remain
alive you wouldn't so your whole life
right now while we're talking about
depends on something
well basically depends on your heart in
the same sense then depends on a random
ticking clock in the world they have no
control over that ticking clock stops
your heart your heart basically stops
that's what it is and that's it so you
don't have to know I must keep attending
this I'm asking now you already set up
the experience allow it to endure so now
your mother might move further there is
a cup of tea or coffee but if I asked
you now 15 seconds later the perception
of the significance of your heart there
has been now left to drift into the
peripheral it's still there
you haven't forgot it because I haven't
forgot it because we've been talking
about it together and we can be silent a
bit longer talk about something else but
actually see there is still a thread
there the heart which we spoke about
like 30 seconds ago now that phenomena
is still there we are not attending to
it yet it's still there
you haven't completely lost it and then
the time will come when you will
completely lose it and that's the
important point
you forget yeah that's what I mean when
you forget about it when you go back to
it you go back to it in the same manner
as it is enduring now notice something I
must I must be I must go over to attend this
I must be I must go over to attend this
no it's already there it's already
determination for your life whether you
tell to yourself that or not doesn't
matter so you want to stop having to
tell that to yourself and you want to
start learning how that thing will tell
it to you because things are general
genuinely impermanent and cannot be on
and cannot be controlled but you can't
see that because you depend on you
telling yourself that things of general
impermanent cannot beyond itself so yeah
you have to stop like that but you have
to see that it has to come from the
thing not from you and you will see that
if you're laughing to do so it's been a
minute and a half now the perception of
the significance of the heart is still
there isn't it it faded but it's still
there that background connection so this we
that background connection so this we
hasn't been lost although we already
went through three different topics on
top of it but it's still there it's
still enduring on the agenda of
peripheral level in both our minds
actually you know that'sthat's my whole
point it's not like some I don't know
it's not like some I don't know
spiritual intuitive knowledge no it's
the clarity of phenomena you know no
that's what we've been talking it's
enduring there you can attend to all
sorts of things but that thing is still
there on its own that's the important
bit that's how you stop putting the
emphasis that's how you shift it on to
the phenomena that has a reason and
enduring normal to me attending it
that's how places of second basically
and when the sense of self is second
it's not a sense of certain tensor self
is always the first the master so in the
background of your mind the perception
of the significance of the beating heart
we stopped we spoke body is it still
there it is isn't it it's all gone and
there hasn't been a single active effort
made I must bring this back no but but
but what we didn't do is clarify the
signature of it and now it's enduring you set it
of it and now it's enduring you set it
up rightly and now it's enduring and
it's still dead actually all this time
it's persisting the same thing is
persisting while it's changing or not
this particular level through discussing
all these various things and that's what
me things we're discussing now are
simultaneous present with the background
that's enduring that it's a difficult
thing from them it changed a different
speed but they're simultaneously there
they don't connect
they don't merge they're simply two
things standing one in the background
from where you look which means if your
attention looks one side is gonna be on
the other side that's just how it works
that's why you can't choose sides that's
why you can look at this all of that
because the options are given do not
much stop thinking about other things
you stopping about anything's you use
the same principle or allow your mind to
get established upon the significance of
that peripheral and then let it go let
you might think other things see now is
there still significance of the hot
present it is and I know it is I know it
is in your mind as well and I and I
can't enter your brain and read your
mind but I can see the phenomena that we
established but but it didn't change a
bit it faded even more now because our
topics are taking us further from it so
we are going to keep introducing the new
significance and then what's gonna
happen is when you look back and think
about the significance of the heart it's
gonna rise as a memory as in the
enduring phenomena has ceased and then
you realize now you have the experience
of what was the enduring phenomena which
now is enduring
and that's how the same significance of
these perceptions can be reestablished
in the fingers now because you don't
have to go through the same motions and
methods to it it's already implied in it
you just need to cry be for your
discernment
it's still there
so you have to keep on topic you have to
keep on topic if you would turn you to
the ecstatically establishing that
significance rightly would sort of
create that enduring context but you
don't have to keep this is a context
this is the context this is the context
context context no it's there you left
it in you and then what do i do then you
don't do anything you know you might
think just make sure it doesn't go into
sensuality you will and quilt that's it
that's all you have to do just prevent
it from going there if he doesn't want
to go there you don't have to do
anything that's how you make your own
sense of self redundant
how's the how's the enduring
significance of the heart is it still
there or has it sufficiently change to
be called a different thing let's do it
now wondering if it it stops to mean
more what do you mean more significance
now you see it's unattractive well no
you can take sure you can take it's a
physical way see different angles yeah
you can see different aspects of it yeah
of course that's how that's all how you
could beyond doubt see if your mind is
established upon the peripheral upon the
nature of an enduring phenomenon
no matter your active movements of your
mind is it is it not is it that all of
that is secondary to that enduring
significance that you've established so
you can't doubt it you can doubt with
your attending but the background of
attention is that which you cannot
attend and you cannot doubt that if you
start discerning it if you keep
confusing it and thinking that you can
attend the background of your attention
in the same sense you think you can see
the eye because of which you see then
yeah you are still affected by that
it has changed quite a bit now the
significance of the beating heart and we
discussed five minutes ago but it's
still there it's still the same thing
you could say no it's still the same
phenomena that's what Nevada was talking
about you know the identity the self
identity of a self enduring phenomenon
the people confused with their own self
identity the identity of that thing it's
still there it's still the same thing
so in that sense you are responsible for
establishing your mind correctly only so
to let go and allow that establishment
to endure if done rightly it will end
you that's how we went to John is well
that's how we went to John is well
that's what he was selling that much
money Karthik among doesn't think our um
entering the Jannah now or I will enter
the jannah he sets up his mind he sets
up the right significance and then the
mind gets established upon the earth the
fimo gentleman and that's why while that
theme is enduring in the same sense the
phenomena of the beating heart now which
is the basically implication of
repulsion impermanence nonsense reality
indifferent sapega all that is implied
in the phenomena we clarified of heart
cannot be on yet is the reason because
of which you are there in the first
place so you establish your mind like
that then you won't be able to think for
as long as such phenomena is enduring of
oh I'm doing this I'm doing that because
it's not selfs and it's not rooted in
you anymore it's rooted in info in the
proper Foundation which is the
foundation that of the uncontrollable
matter the five aggregates they cannot
actually beyond and so on so if it
becomes developed the knowledge is
developed sufficiently enough does it
end this passion this passion is a sign
this passion is the result when a is one
boys a way of the background so cuz
that's not something you attempted but
in one is always aware of the background
yeah whichever that very don't is at a
time and stead the other hand isn't
always mindful you don't be specific no
people think we for as long as people
think mindfulness is virtual end then
they can't comprehend how cannot be
always mindful always mindful and not be
a robot in the same time now this is how
he's mindful because he's he's extent of
his discernment has been developed so
far now that what we speak about this
significance of the beating heart
he's a very low level phenomena from
which can establish your mind imagine you you
can establish your mind imagine you you
discerned within that and within that
and there is always something enduring
for as long as these aggregates don't
break apart so that's what will amend or
he develops mindfulness to the extent
necessary for the final knowledge the
exactly to the extent
so that's how you conduct as I said all
that all the things they were implied in
the in the perception of the beating
heart that's not in your control yet it
determines your whole life
simultaneously while you're alive you
can go further within the same
perception what is the characteristics
what are the limiters of that
significance of that beating heart oh
it's like not my control so my sense of
control fundamentally depends upon the
greater domain of non control of
inaccessible to my control
that's nothing other than an engine so
you develop the perception of
impermanence correctly cannot be own
cannot be appropriate it cannot be
controlled it's impermanent do it
everything is everything implies that
the universal character is the most
universal but as I said if you know
sometimes the mind just won't be sort of
it's getting established upon cuz it's
too subtle and it go to distract you
whatever you bring it down that's why
they wouldn't such a various range of
different approaches think about look at
the dead corpse yeah on some days that
will not be necessary because it would
be enough just to think about a
phenomenon not control and it would be
fully establishing this passion you now
see a show and it'll be pushing and
everything else but on Sundays you want
but you either way
you're developing the same principle so
this do you know that you are developing
correctly we've actually got some way
then the sign of dispassion he's always
there yeah this is the sign of freedom
from suffering will always be there if
the mines probably establish their cars
everything BG experiencing that why
because again you you have you have
shift the emphasis from me and I on to
the the enduring phenomena that exist on
its own so even with the disagreeable
things are ours is like it becomes
inconceivable to become involved in the
personal manner it's just the wind blows
you know the branches fall the Sun
shines their heartbeats people shout
abuse at you it's just it's on the same
level it would have listed it as like
elements to be endured or enduring the
militia speech in her speech is own
like the breath you can breathe
breathing is always there
yeah the intention to breathe maybe to
be more specific
sure well just breathing there you can
say that but I can sit down and do play
with my breath maybe yeah okay but you
want to know knows you want to stop like
now for most people well because they're
too too too too concerned with what they
attend even the people who try to
practice breath is pretty much very
thorough in regards to their other
actions breath goes into the background
but if you bring the breath into the
foreground as in like okay I'm sitting
here breathing in reading in a no great
executive you don't do it as a sense of
I'm gonna be attending every second of
this you bring it to the foreground so
that you will see the background of the
background of the breath for most of the
day-to-day experience breath is in the
background and again you can establish
significance will you be alive with the
breathing stops if your Airways get
blocked No
so you could establish the same
principle as we just did of dispassion
relinquishment non control not self but
seeing the background of your breath oh
you can run on a refine it further and
start seeing the background of the
actual act of breathing and that's how -
artists of the goes which says knowingly
he breathes in knowingly he breathes out
not like I'm breathing in and breathing
in and breathing in a bit now I'm
breathing I'm opening outfitting are we
not know he's breathing in breathing up
and he knows it which means now he's
discerning even more general background
to that because that that's what's
what's in front of him he puts his
mindfulness to the fore as the suit
ourselves okay I'm sitting here I'm not
doing anything else except breathe
I'm not controlling it I'm just doing it
I can do it like this what I can it
doesn't matter what matters is knowing
the background of that doing and that's
how you establish mindfulness of the
bringing mindfulness is synonymous
basically background when you say
mindfulness state background so you can
call mindfulness of reading at
background of the beating it was the
background of the breathing is well
fundamentally comes down to the
knowledge of action any action good
breathing is an action well that would
be the luck if you fully discern it but
what is what is like initially what it
would be the background of the breathing
is then known of your breathing
knowledge of the necessity of breath the
necessity of the body and again when I
say necessity of those things means you
are no necessary these things are
necessary so it's like narrowing down
the field of your concern like I must do
this imagine you get distracted well you
can't get distracted that's what I said
oh you develop this and the body you are
discerning that is that the body is the
body among the bodies as it is the body
that stands for the phenomena of the
body the time
so you use your breathing basically is
like a natural confinement for the
concern of your thought and you become
mindful if properly when you study
setting the background of that
confinement but it you cannot as I said
you deserve the confinement because
breathing is already there whether you
attend do it or not you certainly don't
make a mechanical method out of it what
we're not sure what - forgot my nostril
it's fully just well there is a beggarly
but you're actively looking away from
your leg trying to focus on what's in
front of you so what like when you learn
something to just two equals four you
know that every time you look it 2+2 so
imagine the same principle applied to
the universal nature of experience
whenever you look at anything that has a
reason you see it cessation has the
instead of soda path whatever is the
nature of arising not whatever has a
reason in front of it's impermanent
whatever has the nature of arising means
totally the police peripheral knowledge
the nature is something you cannot
attend you can discern based on things
you're attending
so you discerned them whatever it has
the nature of arising for that reason
has to cease well as the nature whatever
has arisen has the sign of because of
its arising so no because it's gonna
disappear but because it has a reason
so whenever things are rise for you
which is for as long as the five
aggregates exist means you see
impermanence that's why our own trip is
irreversible right view is irreversible
you cannot forget that because
everything contains it everything that's
why it's such a general statement
because that's the most accurate well
you could say whatever is the nature
rising has the nature ceasing because of
that that's it
so that significance that sign is always
there because what it was manifested
exactly and that is its nature that's
why the Dhamma as in the phenomenon and
in the Dhamma is in the teaching is like
the nature of its the phenomena the
phenomenology literally the knowledge of
the phenomenon so whatever has the
nature of manifestation has the nature
of these teaching of the Dhamma as in
the nature of impermanence and so on
because that's like that's the most
genuine the most fundamental now look at
the bridge or now contemplate the body
now I've come to believe the sixth sense
of this dead but if you look at
manifestation well no you look at the
breath you contemplate the body so to
keep discerning this one major
manifestation clearer and clearer much
yeah just when I say the into
manifestation I mean what I said when we
were establishing the significance of
the beating heart already there on its
own manifest state you're not creating
it by attending it you can only attend
it because it's already there in during
you cannot create anything from
nothingness into blank bring it into
being because you are the result of it
your attention is already secondary to
it structurally not as one two three
it's all like within the same reason
basis of the present form pair of the
consciousness it you cannot step outside
of so any movement you make within it
it's within it so you trying to attend
that would require you to step outside
of it and see it as an object but that's
inconceivable and if you keep doing it
it's because you're miss conceiving that
you can do it so the moment you want to
discern these Universal characteristics
onto things not onto you attending and
they exist only when I attended it and
that's how you approved your sensor so
don't you can't step outside of yourself
or there are five aggregates but you can
certainly stop misconceiving them but
that can be done only from the inside
all right
how is a bigger a long-distance shooter
huh there's any kind of form whatsoever
past future bill whatever because T's
all formats abilities with correct
wisdom okay
so shooting the benefit of discernment
the significance of the heart then
within that you can discern what what's
further what's more refined significance
that this beating heart or it implies
which is the significance of Earth
significance of water fire significance
of impermanence significance of non
control so big who is a long distance
shooter is if he doesn't even have to
anymore go through like establish
significance of the heart to discern
these are the modified significance is
his mind is already developed to the
level of discerning we find significance
is in whatever he has a reason and those
defined significance is refined science
are daring permanence four Great
elements and how does the biggest
sharpshooter he goes for the
significance is that fundamental to
freedom from suffering basically is it
yeah this destruction there you go
because that's all that's all it matters
yet you would arrive at that which suit
is it what is it it's the warrior 181 to
a full force
yes yeah look you would arrive at that
through you know contemplating the
independence of the great matter your
dependence on it and so on
you would eventually drain away any
conceit any miss concerning which will
result in for you from suffering oh if
you are shoot precisely yeah you go
straight for freedom from suffering
because that's already implied the most
genuine luck many things on every the
most fundamental they will see see
develop that that's also how economy
would be one deliberated through wisdom
when he discerns only things relevant to
liberation he doesn't develop like all
the channels and everything else
that discerns the right things to the
sufficient extent see that now would you
speak about it for most people who
listen to this it would be quite an
abstract thing but the only reason it's
abstract is because the man hasn't been
developed in regard to that abstraction
so start developing it start deserving
it in a reason things that in your for
you in front of you throughout your
daily life that's because these things
are there they will remain abstract for
as long as you don't see where they are
so you abstract them literally how is a
bigger one who splits a great body
yeah because because the great mass of
ignorance possessing these here these
four qualities is worthy of offerings
and how was the biggest gilded places
his virtuous scene a dangerous life
that's also a will you see the danger
it's in that that peripheral the dangers
in the background the danger is the
implication of what's in front of you
the danger is the context that you
create Patricia doesn't see the dangers
in surety but if you start thinking
about it
discerning it you get to see because it
is actually dangerous that's how you can
develop the danger in the slightest
fault and not become neurotically
obsessed about every little thing that's
in front of you fearing it because
that's not with the faith that's not
what the danger is that's where the
simile of the beautiful tasty beverage
you can't see the poison in it but you
know it which means ultimately the
danger sensuality is rooted in the
background and never can ever come in
front of you and be seen in the same man
that you see object to the senses that's
why people are intoxicated with
sensuality despite experiences always
proving the detection tempo because you
only guard things as real is the things
that you can see through your senses
usually so you want to discern in that
danger as I said never leaves the
peripheral never becomes like oh yeah I
see the danger in my eyes no you still
see the beautiful object but now you
have fully understood and you fully
discern the danger the significance of
the enduring the significance of the
enduring beautiful object is the
peripheral danger Uber's it is it it's
not maybe or like danger come after its
it
the beverage the drink the contains
poison they will kill you you can see
you can smell it it's undetectable and
that's the Buddhist simile I'm not
making this up it's the poison is
undetectable so unless you know that's
poison there you'll be drinking and
that's what people do so you have to
know that poison is there and you have
to stop ignoring the fact that poison is
there and then you get to see that
whatever is beautiful yeah you fully
understood this is dangerous
this poison is there but you can't see the
poison is there but you can't see the
poison you can't extract it and see like
look this is the poison see because that
would then imply that other things you
can see you don't have that poison so
poison is in everything you see hear
smell taste touch it in everything
that's agreeable contains the poison
because it's agreeable you could you
could think that a great ability of
things it's what poison is but that in itself
it's what poison is but that in itself
it's on dangerous isn't it what's
dangerous is you carelessly ingesting
the poison you carelessly welcoming the
ugly ability delighting in it saying
yesterday to the dangers not the result
no no exactly exactly the danger is that
significance of it if you take it then
that danger before you oh it's dangerous
to go to those forests yeah you don't go
but it's dangerous to go to forest it's
like well you know I'll be fine good and
then you go yeah so you say danger
sensuality is if you indulge yeah
exactly that's that's like that's what
the level of perception Bangu increase
yeah well like I suppose somebody to
complete novice train has to start like
rounding it up from such a I'll do it
many lose their money yeah sure those
are reflections that complete our
suitable Papagena will have to go
through in order to begin but that's not
a danger that's why they would would say
you're not free from the shock until the
danger becomes apparent and the dangers
not become apparent if you only wait for
you to even get a sense of danger have
to get through the motion of repeating
how this satisfying sensuality actually
is and that's what the level of
psychologists were like rationalizing
yeah as I said it can help somebody
who's absolutely no ground for practice
but you want to go way beyond that you
want to be able seeing the agreeable
equals seeing the danger or do you
consider the individualized seeing the
agreeable equals knowing the danger that
way whether said knowledge comes
knowledge is secondary to perception but
yeah you can equally have a set
without knowledge being present death so
knowledge is not in perception which
means you can perceive the knowledge but
you can know that which you perceive at
the same time literally a cup or drink
in front of you and you're drinking and
it's very good people told yourself
these people do which is gonna prolong
your life and kill cancer Wow
and then somebody comes to tell you then
it's actually gonna kill you I'm gonna
show it in your life see both could be
right as in you don't know which one's
right but the fact now that he has been
placed into doubt that it's good for you
it's actually enough for you to back off
from it Oh better not take any chances
perhaps I don't need a longer life it's
long because you know it might actually
shorten it let alone if actually becomes
apparent that no the second guy was
right it will it will kill you quicker
it will ruin you
so the danger here the cup the content
nothing's changed it's all in front of
you your experience on the point exactly
you started selling the danger even in
might that's what I'm saying when did
you don't know for yourself that it's
good for you that's already dangerous
and if you start thinking like that the
danger will become apparent the danger
that is actually there but you can't see
that until you are elevated as in you
can't do that for yourself you have to
take it on trust let's ensure it is
dangerous and start regarding it as such
and because it is dangerous
your way of regarding it will eventually
mirror how it is and you get to
understand it so sensuality as in you
want to see sensuality go on you want to
see it in front of you say sure sure the
domain of sensuality of sensual
infection the domain of seeking pleasure
on the grounds of your own body smell
taste sight smell taste touch
the main optional situation all of that
essential yet and now the peripheral of
that perception of sensuality is the
knowledge of the danger is the
significance of the danger
it's the implication of the danger
knowledge of the tank what are you
looking for well first if you don't if
you don't discern the phenomenon of
sensuality you're not gonna in the same sense as I
you're not gonna in the same sense as I
said mindfulness of breathing it's like
a confinement that represents all the
other actions you do in your life on
account of your breathing but then
you're not doing that confinement you
will descend the Pegram of their
confinement then they mix everything
inferior to that even clearer so in the
same sense you will discern the extent
of sensuality in order to discern a
pattern of the danger that's why the
Buddha would all be stopped and say the
gratification has been of sensuality has
been understood the danger has become
apparent yeah no but the danger has
become apparent and then I understood by
understanding the extent of sensuality
by the standing is gratification then
the background of that the danger
becomes clear but not before you
understand the extent of of basically
physical pleasures craving for physical
products and you can only understand the
extent if you start looking for the
extent and the extent the gratification
of sexuality is not in a particular
engagement with the sensuality it's in
the background of your particular
engagement the Super's yeah so those
possibilities exactly so by saying no to
the particular engagement of sensuality
what no sir there are obviously
sensualities that you cannot be mindful
of the ones that take mind too far out
such as non celibacy killing lying
stealing so you are been doing that but
now you have to eat within that you
gotta get present taste in your mouth
buddy wanna spit this out cuz it's too
Pleasant no you don't see the
gratification there you fear everything
you spit in your drink but that's not
what sociology is sensuality is your
attitude in regard to the object you're
attending so if all you do is that
two things you're never gonna see your
attitude in regard to it so now you live
restraint you're not breaking up in you
see the danger in the slightest fault
when you encounter agreeable things at
the base for sexuality that's when you
start looking for the background of that
you allow it to arise well the taste is
in my mother but it doesn't say spit the
food he said no eat mindfully as it eats
remain eat while you're aware of the
background of your pleasant taste don't
get absorbed with the pleasant taste and
people try to not get absorber present
days by you know focusing on other
things or avoiding or twisting their
tongue to avoid the taste and whatnot no
that's equally on the same footing where
the taste is you want to just know the
background of the present taste that
already clarifying the extent of
gratification the clearly the extent of
gratification the perception of
gratification becomes the significance
of the danger becomes clear and the
gratification became clear the danger
has been seen has become apparent and
then the way out from sensuality and the
gratification is automatic
so to see the extent to see the
possibilities
first you have to be restrained not give
in to distraction because if you
intentionally give in to sensuality yeah
you can't establish that mindfulness
because your intention already distorted
it it's already inverted diverted
but if agreeable things that the base
for sexuality come to you without your
intention necessarily being looted in in
seeking the pleasure like in them that's
where you start discerning the
peripheral that's where the
gratification of sensuality becomes
clear that's why sila has to come first
it's just not optional
but that's only like the problem is with
people sila comes first and then the
denial of any any I need anything
Pleasant that comes even if it's not
seek by you becomes the next attitude oh
I want this like this taste is way too
nice so I only need things that I hate
but you you are basically misconceiving
central you think sexualities in the
actual taste and you think that by
avoiding taste to avoid sensuality no
you just obscure it further so you were
free from sensuality
you would be what we'd have what if you
had right view every from centrality
you'll be honored
but if you if you don't have the right
view you could be free from society and
then you will need very very little
instruction to get the right view
because you've already done 80% of the
work 80% of the fundamental existential
distraction which is the senses have
been tamed and surmounted and understood
because if you see things as whatever
has arisen the back the background is it
will cease yeah and then you turn your
mind to what is the extent of sensuality
exactly you see the same principle and
also those who don't see that principle
but have seen the sensuality they have
removed pretty much the sole reason for
not seeing impermanence like virtually
sensuality is the main reason because
sensuality is the results in distraction
and everything else so you have removed
that you have understood that you
develop your money in regard to it you
have seen the peripheral of that domain
you've seen the danger in it and then
you just need somebody to tell you what
the impermanence of phenomena is and you
will be like well you wouldn't you you
will immediately called straight to
anagram basically what even I don't know
cuz you already download the work when
you said it it's a danger of sensuality
he's being he's being pulled in you in
the foreground yeah yeah see already
record it but you want to see that now
notice something notice a statement that
you made but you actually want to see it
coming from that sensuality but in order
to see yeah you have to be clarifying
that understanding even those statements
for yourself the more you clarified the
more of the significance is being
clarified and then you will get to
recognize it because I will say the
fundamental danger of sensuality is
exactly that you cannot remain not
pulled not distorted by the foreground
you cannot sew this I wanted to say that
the danger of sensuality is no let me
say but I thought the mid was slightly
wrong saying this is the result of
sensuality is the fact that you are
pulled into the sense perceptions
essential world and therefore I'm not
able to be mindful yeah I'm not you are
confused you are you are sure you that
is like a coupe accumulative result of
sort of not not abandoning century
gauging with it
the danger is being lost that you will
be well the danger is not being free
yeah lost in ignorance not free
you're only free when you surround the
danger you're only free when you smiled
ignorance so if you don't semantics
you're not free and that that's the
dangerous I'm sorry not free means
samsara so am I not
is that not men am I not then seeing
danger essentially what do you perceive
it well you are seeing to some extent
sure but you wanna see that to the point
of where you have completely completely
sort of any desire to words it has faded
away toward sensual enjoyment and it
will fade away when the danger becomes
perception of danger basically that
background implication significance of
de turista
develop to the extent necessary whereby
no matter how much you get distracted
you never ever go back to the point of
being distracted that you actually want
sensuality in the same sense like you
vomit you want me the food that you ate
you'll never ever gonna get so hungry to
eat that stuff it's moldy and filthy and
mixed with soil it's just it's just not
perceived its edible anymore that's how
far you want to go with sensuality he
sees to be perceived as body of
engagement it's actually the opposite
non engagement is what worthy non
engagement is what freedom is engagement
is death results in death implies that
makes you're liable to death literally
so if you literally like you wouldn't be
killed if somebody comes and shoot you
in the head that's not that death is
sending your mind back down the senses
that's how you get killed because if you
take your mind away from the senses you
surmount sensuality even if somebody
comes in shoot you in the head you are
not killed so that's what I said those
who are not mindful
those who are not properly established
upon the peripheral background a servant
of that significance they are as if they
are already dead
because if you see the extent of
sensuality then you know very well when
when you step into we cannot be done
incidentally it's always a choice
yeah it's always a choice so with these
if you see the extensive sensuality you
you will see your choice yeah the choice
if you're aware of the background you
are aware of you about to make a choice
you're one of the possibilities to
choose which means you realize all that
I'm holding responsible I'm already
choosing basically direction of
sensuality even before I directly engage
with it so it's my scene the choice of
sentiment it sure does seem extended you
seen the examples of shots in the
background especially disturbing gradual
significance oh yeah taking
responsibility for the choice that's
another approach the same thing